Hi and welcome to step two of the tribe success path. Step two is called activate the application
and the reason we call it that is we're taking all the knowledge you learned in step one
and we're learning to apply it to exam style questions. Now it's really important that we
do that topic by topic because each topic has a different set of exam techniques and a different
set of exam tips that will really help you augment your grade. So it's important that you activate
the application for each topic. The way we're going to do that is you're going to download
the past paper questions below and I've handpicked them to relate exactly to what we've just learned.
You're going to complete those questions, you're going to put your head down, you're going to work
really hard and complete those questions. Once you've completed those questions you're going to
watch me screencast the answers to most of them in the rest of this tutorial. Now the reason I've
screencast the answer to about two thirds of these questions and not the last third
is we need to start letting you go and what that means is I have to teach you all my exam tips,
I have to teach you all my exam techniques, you have to start taking them in and applying them
and that's step three of the tribe success path that's propel your progress. So you have to do
some work in this step, you have to learn my exam techniques, learn my tips and do your own work
for step three to work effectively. So once you've written out the answers to these
past paper questions keep them and take them on to step three. Okay let's go.
Here we're looking at past paper questions that relate to A1 kinematics and these questions
have been taken from past papers in the years 2016 to 2022. There are a range of types of
questions here, quite a lot of multiple choice questions which you'll of course find in paper
1a of your exams and a few calculate style questions that you'd find in paper 2. A little
note about the multiple choice questions in the previous specification, you weren't allowed a
calculator in the previous specification for your multiple choice questions and in your exams you
will be allowed a calculator. So you'll find that these multiple choice questions have very simple
maths in them but the concepts will be the same sort of concepts that you'll meet in your paper
1 section a. Without further ado let's get going. Question one, an aircraft is moving horizontally,
a parachutist leaves the aircraft and a few seconds later opens her parachute. Which graph
shows the variation of vertical speed with time for the parachutist from the time she
leaves the aircraft until just before landing? So let's have a think about this, we'll draw
a diagram. That's our aeroplane. Our parachutist is going to do this when she jumps out but we've
been told only to look at the vertical speed. So we're looking at projectile motion, horizontal
projection but we're actually only considering the vertical speed and we know that the vertical
speed of this parachutist will increase because she's falling under the influence of gravity.
So we expect her speed or vertical speed to increase. Now if you look at these graphs
c and d show the vertical speed decreasing so we know it's not c or d we can get rid of them
straight away. What's going to happen is she's going to experience drag so she will be moving
downwards and her weight force will be like this and her upward force is drag and as she
gets faster this drag force gets bigger and bigger and eventually they'll balance each other
which means it'll have a constant speed and both of these graphs are showing to the point where
constant speed is. What you've got to remember is is that this lady is going to open her parachute
and once she opens her parachute she will instantly decrease in speed and that is the
graph that shows this so question 1a. Question two, a car moves north at a constant speed of
three meters per second for 20 seconds and then east at a constant speed of four meters per second
for 20 seconds also. What is the average speed of the car? Well by telling you the directions of
these speeds they're tricking you because they don't care they just want to know what the
speed is and the average speed of the car can be found with the equation total distance covered
over total time. Okay so the total distance covered here will be distance equals speed
times time so that'll be 60 meters and the total distance covered here that will be 80 meters
so the average speed is 140 divided by the total time which is 20 plus 20 that's 40.
That will be 3.5 meters per second and our answer is 2c. Question three, an object of weight w
are you noticing I'm drawing a diagram every time and remember I said drawing a diagram is
really important in fact if you don't draw a diagram you're likely to miss something drawing
a diagram at all times. An object of weight w is falling vertically at a constant speed
when you see the word constant speed you should be thinking the phrase balanced forces
constant speed means balanced forces which means that w has a balanced force up the way of drag
and it equals the weight force what is the magnitude of the drag force on the object
it's the same as the weight force so it's question 3c. Question four, a tennis ball is hit
with a racket from a point 1.5 meters above the floor the ceiling is 8 meters above the floor
the initial velocity of the ball is 50 meters per second at 50 degrees to the horizontal
assume the air resistance is negligible so this distance here by very simple maths is 6.5 meters
and question e and this is a longer extended question which you'd find in paper two
it's determined whether the ball will hit the ceiling now the ball will hit the ceiling if
its maximum height is greater than 6.5 meters so let's find what the maximum height of this
ball will be. We are dealing with a projectile so we use vertical and horizontal sides
from the vertical we're interested in stupid equations and on the horizontal we're interested
in the speed equals distance over time equation but actually we don't really care about horizontal
because we're only interested in how high it's going to go. We know its initial speed is 15
sine 50 because we only want the vertical component of this final velocity we know that
the final speed at its maximum height here maximum height the final speed is zero so let's put zero
we've automatically chosen upwards as positive because we've given u it's moving up the way
we've given that positive value so that means acceleration which is traveling in the other
direction is going to be negative so minus 9.8 and t doesn't really matter to us we can use the
equation v squared equals u squared plus 2a s and we want to find out what s is so let's plug in our
data 0 equals 15 sine 50 squared plus 2 times minus 9.8 times s that's going to give us
0 equals 132.04 minus 19.6 s we're going to take the 132 over to this side so minus
132.04 equals minus 1 19.6 s and we can work out s by dividing by 19.6 so s is equal to 6.7 meters
6.7 is more than 6.5 so the bowl will hit the ceiling. Question five which of the following
is a scalar quantity well velocity is not momentum is not acceleration is not kinetic energy is
energy is a scalar quantity you just have to learn these quantities folks you've got to learn
which is a scalar and which is a vector boring but that's the way to do it. Question six an object
is released from rest in the gravitational field of earth air resistance is negligible how far does
the object move so we want to know what s is during the fourth second of its motion
turn during the fourth second means how far does it move between three and four seconds
so what we want to do is we want to find out how far it's travelled in three seconds
how far it's travelled in four seconds and then subtract it to find this distance here
okay so for this we're going to use the Suvak equations it's a free falling object in the
gravitational field let's say downwards is positive that means that acceleration is 10
notice that I'm using 10 instead of 9.8 here or 9.8 one that's because calling it 10 or 9.8 is
going to make no difference in terms of what these four answers are so I can afford to
approximate here doesn't matter if it's 9.8 or not all right so u is zero because it's moved from
rest we want to know what the distance is after three seconds so we're going to use s equals ut
plus a half at squared and this goes to zero because u is zero so it's a half times 10
times three squared so it's five times nine which is 45 meters so in three seconds it travels
45 meters in four seconds it travels times 10 times four squared so that's five times 16
which is 80 meters so it travels 80 meters in four seconds so in the fourth second
it travels 80 minus 45 which is 35 meters the answer is question 6c another one of these questions
question seven which is a vector quantity temperature is not electric current is not pressure is in a gas
pressure can go any direction magnetic field definitely does have a direction so I'm going
to say 7d question 8 a ball is tossed vertically upwards with a speed of five meters per second
after how many seconds will the ball return to its initial position so what it does is this
and there it starts and it's a SUVA equation because it's an object in the earth's
gravitational field let's choose downwards as positive okay so that means you can use
10 is downwards we know that the initial speed is minus five because this is going up the way so
upward is positive how many seconds will the ball return to its initial position ahahaha
when it gets back to here s is equal to zero because it hasn't traveled any displacement
so we want to know the time s equals ut plus a half at squared zero equals minus five t
plus a half times 10 t squared so zero equals minus five t plus five t squared
let's take this fat sorry you saw me make a mistake there easily done let's write that out again
zero equals minus five t plus five t squared let's take that over to there five t equals
five t squared they cancel one of these cancels so one equals t the amount of time it takes to
return to its initial position is one question eight b question nine a projectile is fired
horizontally from the top of a cliff the projectile hits the ground four seconds later at a distance
of whoops at a distance of two kilometers from the base of the cliff so that distance there is
two thousand meters and it takes that's distance horizontal and it takes four seconds for that to
happen what is the height of the cliff so we're looking at vertical motion so vertical motion is
suvat we want we know that the vertical velocity is zero because it's fired horizontally okay so we
can put zero there we want to know what the height of the cliff is we know that if we take
downward just positive the acceleration is equal to 10 meters per second squared and we also know
that it takes four seconds to hit the bottom so actually we've got everything we need s equals
ut plus a half at squared s equals a half times 10 times four squared which is five times 60 which
we did earlier 80 so s height of the cliff is 80 meters question nine b question 10 a glider is an
aircraft with no engine to be launched a glider is uniformly accelerated from rest by a cable
pulled by a motor that exerts a horizontal force on the glider throughout their launch
the glider reaches its launch speed of 27 meters per second after accelerating for 11 seconds
assume that the glider moves horizontally until it leaves the ground calculate the total distance
traveled by the glider before it leaves the ground because they've said uniformly accelerated we know
it's going in a straight line we can use the equations of motion here so write down the word
suvat we want to know the distance it travels like the length of the runway we know that it's
being accelerated from rest we know that its final speed is 27 meters per second and we know
that it takes 11 seconds for that to happen so the equation we want to use is s equals u plus v over
two t you can get that from your data booklet um so we got zero plus 27 over two times 11 and that gives
us 148.5 meters everything in the data is given to three significant figures so you should give
the question you would find that in paper two now you would always find these as the start of a much
longer question it's actually very difficult to find a kinematics question that's very involved
because they always tend to be the starter question question 11 an object is released from
a stationary hot air balloon at height h above the ground an identical object is released at
height h above the ground from another balloon that is rising at a constant speed okay constant
speed that means something air resistance is negligible what does not increase for the object
released from the rising balloon oh that's so easy acceleration is always as we assume within
the gravitational field nine point eight meters per second it's the same for every object so that
was a very easy question in the end question 12 a river flows north a boat crosses the river
so that it only moves in the direction east of its starting point what is the direction
in which the boat must be steered okay so the river's flowing north
and the boat only moves in the direction east so its resultant velocity is going that way
so what way must it be steered so that the resultant velocity is east now we must add
two vectors tip to tail and one of them has to be north resulting in a velocity that's east so
the resultant vector is east the vector that must be steered that adds up with north to get
to the point where the object is protected vertically upwards at time t equals not
air resistance is negligible the object passes the same point above its starting position
at times two and eight so it looks like this t equals not here at this point here
two seconds it hits that point and it's way back down at eight seconds it hits that point
now if air resistance is negligible and it takes two seconds to get from here to here
it makes sense that it takes two seconds to get from here to here so the whole time of the journey
is 10 seconds let's see what we can do with that we also know we're using a suvat equation
because it's an object in free fall in the earth's gravitational field let's choose
upwards as positive and downwards as negative so anything acting upwards is positive anything
acting downwards is negative well we know that gravity is working downwards so that'll be minus
10 the time of the whole journey is 10 seconds we want to know what the initial speed is and we
know that the vertical displacement is zero meters because it's traveled all the way up
and traveled all the way back down but vertically it's gone nowhere so let's use s equals ut
plus a half at squared zero equals u times 10 plus a half times minus 10 times
10 squared which is 100 so we've got zero equals 10u minus 500 let's take that over minus 10u equals
minus 500 so u equals 50 meters per second the answer is a question 14 the velocities vx and vy
minus vy do you remember that trick i taught you in math skills for a1 kinematics how to subtract
vectors well you subtract vectors by instead of writing vx minus vy you write vx plus minus vy
and what that means is you want to change the direction of vy so instead of thinking it goes
that way it now goes this way okay so you want to add them tip to tail now so we take vx like
this and we add it tip to tail to vy like this and the resultant vector is from the start of vx
to the end of vy and we're looking at vector d question 15 an elastic climbing rope is tested
by fixing one end of the rope to the top of a crane the other end of the rope is connected
to a block which is initially at position a the block is released from rest the mass of
the rope is negligible the unextended length of the rope is 60 meters from position a to position
b the block falls freely at position b the rope starts to extend calculate the speed of the block
at position b so between a and b we know that the block falls freely it will accelerate under
the force of gravity in our earth's gravitational field so we're using the suvat equations we want
to know what the final velocity is we know that the initial velocity is zero meters per second
it's falling from rest let's choose downward as positive that means our acceleration due to
gravity is 9.81 meters per second squared and it falls a distance of 60 meters you may notice that
i flip between 9.8 9.81 and 10 for gravity okay i tend to use 10 in multiple choice questions
as i've explained before in paper two questions you really should use 9.81 okay so just you guys
use 9.81 okay so we're going to use this equation here v squared equals u squared plus 2 a s
v squared equals zero squared plus two times 9.81 times 60 which gives us v squared equals one one
seven one two and v is equal to 34.3 meters per second i think we should conduct a
reasonableness check on this is it reasonable that a block would travel at 34.3 meters per second
yes it is is it reasonable that a block would travel at 1177 meters per second well no it's
not quite a lot of people might forget to square root the v and if you forget to do that fair
enough but you should always look at your answer and say is it reasonable because it was not
reasonable it means you've probably forgotten to do something okay our answer here is 34.3
we've given it to three significant figures because the data at most is at three significant
figures question 16 a truck has an initial speed of 20 meters per second it decelerates
at four meters per second what is the distance taken by the truck to stop we can see that
this has this truck has a constant deceleration in a straight line that means we can use the
equations of motion so we write down our all our quantities in the equations of motion that's
suvat we want to find out what the distance taken to stop is let's have a think about this
truck it's traveling in that direction but the acceleration will be traveling in that direction
let's say anything that way is positive and anything that way is negative okay so the initial
speed is 20 meters per second the final speed will be zero because it's come to a stop and the
acceleration will be minus four meters per second squared the equation we'll want to use is v squared
equals u squared plus 2a s let's rearrange for s v squared minus u squared over 2a equals s
okay the final speed is zero minus the initial speed which is 20 squared
over two times a which is two times minus four equals s so we have minus 400 over minus eight
gives us s equals 50 meters the answer is c question 17 a runner starts from rest and accelerates
at a constant rate throughout a race which graph shows the variation of speed v of the runner with
the distance traveled this question is telling us that this is a constant acceleration in a straight
line so we can deal with suvat equations here we're looking at these five quantities we know
that the acceleration is constant and we know the initial speed is zero if we can find a mathematical
relationship between v and s we can translate that mathematical relationship into a graphical form
let's you look at this equation here v squared equals u squared plus 2a s
u is zero so what we find is v squared equals 2a s this is a constant okay so let's say v squared
equals a constant k s now on the y axis in these graphs we have v so we could say y squared equals
k x and the s is on the x axis and mathematically what would a y squared proportional to x graph
look like well we know that x equals y squared looks like this and we know that these are linear
graphs there's no squared proportionalities in there so it must be this one question 17 a
question 18 a projectile is fired at an angle to the horizontal air resistance is negligible
the path of the projectile is shown below and we've got a displacement displacement graph here
which gives the magnitude of the horizontal component and the magnitude of the vertical
component of velocity of the projectile between o and p well easy we know that the
horizontal component of velocity is always constant so we get rid of c and d okay and between
o and p the projectile is clearly falling back down towards the ground which means its vertical
component of velocity is increasing the answer is a this is about to get a bit trickier with the
higher level question on this one question 19 a projectile is fired at an angle to the horizontal
the path of the projectile is shown now can you see the projectile looks different
from that in question 18 the projectile now includes air resistance which gives the magnitude
of the horizontal component and the magnitude of the vertical component of velocity of the
projectile between o and p right the horizontal component does not stay constant anymore because
air resistance slows it down horizontally so we're looking between a and b but we know that at o
the projectile has reached its maximum height at zero at that stage in terms of the vertical
velocity and it is going to accelerate towards the ground so our magnitude of the vertical
component of velocity will increase our answer is a question 20 a skydiver is falling at
terminal speed when she opens her parachute so she's at terminal speed that means there's
balanced forces i don't know if that's going to mean anything but i'll draw that there just to
remind me what are the direction of her velocity vector and the direction of our acceleration
vector before she reaches a new terminal speed it's got nothing to do with forces
the velocity vector is always going to be downwards at no stage
will this lady be traveling back up okay but as the parachute opens her acceleration
will no longer be downwards because she decelerates very quickly which means the force applied by
her parachute causes a deceleration acceleration in the opposite direction making her slow down
so at that point the acceleration vector is upwards velocity vector is downwards
so the answer is 20 c since recording the original video some people have struggled with question 22
24 and 29 so i've added this part onto the tutorial just to help you just in case it's
the same problem that you're having question 22 a ball is thrown upwards at an angle to the
straight line that's horizontal ball is thrown upwards and the angle is here
air resistance is negligible which statement about the motion of the ball is correct before we go
any further let's just draw the trajectory of the ball the ball will do this a the acceleration
of the ball changes throughout its flight well that's not true the acceleration of the ball
because air resistance is negligible the acceleration of the ball at all points
is g or 9.8 meters per second downwards so it's not that one the velocity of the ball
changes during its flight well yes the velocity changes let's put a tick next to that and make
sure the other two are incorrect the acceleration of the ball is zero at the highest point no
that's not true the acceleration is always g downwards and finally the velocity of the ball
is zero at its highest point ah now this is where a lot of people might struggle because when the
ball is released it has a vertical component of velocity and it has a horizontal component
of velocity v h and that's v vertical v h is constant it doesn't change
so at the maximum point here there still has velocity v h which is the same as the velocity
v h down there v v does change that the vertical velocity does change it starts off at a maximum
here at the start and at this point at the maximum height v v is equal to zero so i think
some people might look at this one and think that's correct but it's not because the
horizontal velocity component is always constant just an aside here if you're looking at a ball being
thrown vertically upwards and then down there's no horizontal element to that so the v at the top
is equal to zero because there's no horizontal element so if you're looking at a ball being
thrown vertically upwards and then down then the velocity at the top is zero we're safe to see that
but as soon as we go to a projectile then there's always a horizontal component of velocity meaning
the velocity at the top is not quite zero the vertical velocity is question 24 a girl throws
an object horizontally at time t equals not the air resistance can be ignored at t equals 0.5 seconds
the object travels horizontally a distance x in meters while it falls vertically through a distance
y in meters what is the initial velocity of the object and the vertical distance fallen let's
draw a little diagram we've got the cliff here we've got the ball being thrown off the cliff like this
and it has an initial velocity of oh we don't know we want to find that out the trajectory of
the ball will look like this and we want to find the initial velocity and the vertical distance
well the initial velocity is just a horizontal component of velocity at the very start the
initial velocity doesn't have any vertical component yet because gravity hasn't had a chance to accelerate
it so our initial velocity is just going to be the horizontal velocity which is v equals distance over
time we know it travels x divided by 0.5 which is equal to 2x so the initial velocity is 2x
so it's c or d to find the vertical distance fallen we're going to have to take two calculations
into account first of all we're looking at vertical velocity only so we'll be using the
so that equations and because the answers are given in terms of y we first need to work out
what y is so we know that the initial velocity vertical velocity of this object will be zero
meters per second i don't really care about the final velocity we know that the acceleration is
10 meters per second and i'm using 10 because it's a multiple choice question and our
test or time here is 0.5 seconds so s equals ut plus a half at squared y because s is equal to y
distance fallen is equal to that goes to zero a half times 10 times that 0.5 squared so that gives
us five times 0.25 so five times 0.25 which gives us 1.25 y so in half a second that's how far the
object has fallen but the vertical distance fallen at t equals one second we have to do the same so we
have to do s equals don't know u equals zero v don't care a equals 10 meters per second
squared and t equals one second so s equals a half a t squared s equals a half times 10
times one squared s equals five and if we divide five divided by 1.25 that gives us four so the
answer is four y or y our answer is d let me remind you that not all multiple choice questions will be
easy some of them will have multiple steps and multiple steps means you have to carry out more
than one calculation and in this case it was three calculations some of them will just take time
question 29 a large stone is dropped from a tall building what is correct about the speed of the
stone after one second now there's something missing here the thing that is missing here
is ignore air resistance it always says ignore air resistance and in this case it hasn't said
ignore air resistance so in this case we have to consider
air resistance let's draw got the building
got a stone being dropped it's only under the influence of vertical motion we're looking at
savi equations which means when there's no air resistance this object will accelerate or the
rate of change of velocity will be 9.81 meters per second squared however that's always where we
ignore air resistance in this case we're not ignoring the air resistance now given that as
that stone falls faster and faster the force back upwards on it the air resistance force will be
bigger and bigger that tells us that the acceleration due to gravity or the acceleration
which is the rate of change of velocity will decrease so what is correct about the speed of
the stone it's increasing because it's getting faster so it's c or d but it's at a decreasing
rate because the acceleration is decreasing due to air resistance so the answer is d